{
  "title": "Engineering_Mathematics - Calculus — Slot 3 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Calculus — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>The value of the integral given below is <br> \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi }x^{2}cosxdx\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(-2\\pi\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\pi\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(-\\pi\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2\\pi\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(-2\\pi\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2081/gate2014-3-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>If \\(\\int_{0}^{2\\pi}|x sinx| dx=k \\pi\\), then the value of k is equal to _______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "4",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2040/gate2014-3-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The function \\(f(x)=x sin x\\) satisfies the following equation: \\(f''(x)+f(x)+tcos x=0\\). The value of t is______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "-2",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1924/gate2014-1-46#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Let the function <br> \\(f(\\theta)=\\begin{vmatrix} sin\\theta &amp; cos\\theta &amp; tan\\theta \\\\ sin(\\frac{\\pi}{6}) &amp; cos(\\frac{\\pi}{6}) &amp; tan(\\frac{\\pi}{6})\\\\ sin(\\frac{\\pi}{3})&amp; cos(\\frac{\\pi}{3}) &amp; tan(\\frac{\\pi}{3}) \\end{vmatrix}\\) <br>  where \\(\\theta \\in [\\frac{\\pi}{6},\\frac{\\pi}{3}]\\) and \\(f'(\\theta )\\) denote the derivative of  f with respect to \\(\\theta\\) . Which of the following\nstatements is/are TRUE? <br>(I) There existrs \\(\\theta \\in (\\frac{\\pi}{6},\\frac{\\pi}{3})\\) such that \\(f'(\\theta )=0\\) <br> (I) There existrs \\(\\theta \\in (\\frac{\\pi}{6},\\frac{\\pi}{3})\\) such that \\(f'(\\theta )\\neq 0\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both I and II</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither I nor II</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Both I and II</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1763/gate2014-1-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>What is the least value of the function \\(f(x) = 2x^{2}-8x-3\\) in the interval [0, 5]? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>-15</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>7</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>-11</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>-11</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/44161/isro-2013-49\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following functions is continuous at x = 3? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f(x)=\\left\\{\\begin{matrix} 2, &amp; if \\; x=3\\\\ x-1,&amp; if \\;  x \\gt 3\\\\ \\frac{x+3}{3},&amp;if \\; x \\lt 3 \\end{matrix}\\right.\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(f(x)=\\left\\{\\begin{matrix} 4, &amp; if \\; x=3\\\\ 8-x&amp;if \\;  x\\neq 3 \\end{matrix}\\right.\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(f(x)=\\left\\{\\begin{matrix} x+3, &amp; if  \\; x\\leq 3\\\\ x-4&amp;if \\; x \\gt  3 \\end{matrix}\\right.\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(f(x)=\\frac{1}{x^{3}-27}, if \\; x\\neq 3\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f(x)=\\left\\{\\begin{matrix} 2, &amp; if \\; x=3\\\\ x-1,&amp; if \\;  x \\gt 3\\\\ \\frac{x+3}{3},&amp;if \\; x \\lt 3 \\end{matrix}\\right.\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1533/gate2013-22#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Consider the function f(x)=sin(x) in the interval x \\(\\in [\\pi/4, 7\\pi/4]\\). The number and location(s) of the local minima of this function are <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>One, at \\(\\pi\\)/2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>One, at 3\\(\\pi\\)/2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Two, at \\(\\pi\\)/2 and 3\\(\\pi\\)/2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Two, at \\(\\pi\\)/4 and 3\\(\\pi\\)/2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Two, at \\(\\pi\\)/4 and 3\\(\\pi\\)/2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/41/gate2012-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>n-th derivative of \\(x^n\\) is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(nx^{n-1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(n^n.n!\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(nx^n!\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>n!</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>n!</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52827/isro2011-59\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Given \\(i=\\sqrt{-1}\\), what will be the evaluation of the definite integral \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi /2}\\frac{cosx + i sinx}{cosx -i sinx} dx\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>i</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(-i\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>i</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2133/gate2011-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The weight of a sequence \\(a_{0},a_{1},...,a_{n-1}\\) of real numbers is defined as \\(a_{0}+a_{1}/2+...+a_{n-1}/2^{n-1}\\) A subsequence of a sequence is obtained by deleting some elements from the sequence, keeping the order of the remaining elements\nthe same. Let X denote the maximum possible weight of a subsequence of\n\\(a_{0},a_{1},...,a_{n-1}\\) and Y the maximum possible weight of a subsequence of \\(a_{0},a_{1},...,a_{n-1}\\). Then X is equal to <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>max(Y,\\(a_{0}\\)+Y)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>max(Y,\\(a_{0}\\)+Y/2)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>max(Y,\\(a_{0}\\)+2Y)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(a_{0}\\)+Y/2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>max(Y,\\(a_{0}\\)+Y/2)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2208/gate2010-34#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>What is the value of \\(\\lim_{n\\rightarrow \\infty }(1-\\frac{1}{n})^{2n}\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(e^{-2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(e^{-1/2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(e^{-2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1151/gate2010-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>The value of x at which y is minimum for \\(y=x^2 -3x +1\\) is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>-3/2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>3/2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-5/4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>3/2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50479/isro2009-50\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>\\(x=a \\cos(t), y=b \\sin(t)\\) is the parametric form of <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Ellipse</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Hyperbola</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Circle</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Parabola</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Ellipse</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50478/isro2009-49\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>The formula \\(\\int\\limits_{x0}^{xa} y(n) dx \\simeq h/2 (y_0 + 2y_1 + \\dots +2y_{n-1} + y_n) - h/12 (\\triangledown y_n - \\triangle y_0)\\)<br>\n\\(- h/24 (\\triangledown ^2 y_n + \\triangle ^2 y_0) -19h/720 (\\triangledown ^3 y_n - \\triangle ^3 y_0) \\dots\\) is called <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Simpson rule</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Trapezoidal rule</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Romberg's rule</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Gregory's formula</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Trapezoidal rule</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50474/isro2009-47\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statement is correct <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\triangle (U_k V_k) = U_k \\triangle V_k + V_k \\triangle U_k\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\triangle (U_k V_k) = U_{k+1} \\triangle V_k + V_{k+1} \\triangle U_k\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\triangle (U_k V_k) = V_{k+1} \\triangle U_k + U_k \\triangle V_k\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\triangle (U_k V_k) = U_{k+1} \\triangle V_k + V_k \\triangle U_k\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\triangle (U_k V_k) = U_{k+1} \\triangle V_k + V_{k+1} \\triangle U_k\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/48070/isro2009-45\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}